A Guide to the Florence Sabin papers, Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research Scientific Staff FA197
Rockefeller Archive Center
Florence R. Sabin papers, Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research Scientific Staff
undated
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller University
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
Sabin, Florence Rena
FA197
2 Cubic Feet
2 boxes, and assorted other materials
Biographical/Historical note
Florence Rena Sabin (1871-1953) physician and scientist in pathology and bacteriology at the Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research from 1925 until retirement as Member Emeritus in 1938.
Biographical note
1871 Born November 9, Central City, Colorado
1893 B.S. Smith College
1893-1895 Taught mathematics at Wolfe. Hall, Denver
1895-1896 Substitute instructor in zoology, Smith College
1900 M.D. Johns Hopkins School of Medicine
1900-1901 Intern Johns Hopkins Hospital
1902 Assistant instructor Anatomy, Johns Hopkins School of Medicine
1903 Prize of the Naples Table Association
1903-1905 Associate in Anatomy, Johns Hopkins School of Medicine
1905-1917 Associate Professor Anatomy, Johns Hopkins School of Medicine
1910 Honorary Sc. D. Smith College
1917-1925 Professor of Histology, Johns Hopkins School of Medicine
1925 Member, Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research, New York
1926 Honorary Sc. D. University of Michigan
1929 Annual Achievement Award, Pictorial Review
1929 Honorary Sc. D. Mt. Holyoke College
1931 Honorary LL. D. Goucher College
1931 Named one of 12 most eminent living women, Good Housekeeping magazine
1932 National achievement award, Chi Omega Society
1933 Honorary Sc. D. New York University
1933 Honorary Sc. D. Wilson College
1934 Honorary Sc. D. Syracuse University
1935 Honorary Sc. D. University of Colorado
1935 M. Carey Thomas Prize, Bryn Mawr College
1935 Named on Carrie Chapman Catt's annual list 10 outstanding women
1937 Honorary Sc. D. University of Pennsylvania
1937 Honorary Sc. D. Oberlin College
1938 Honorary Sc. D. Russell Sage College
1938 Member Emeritus, RI, Retired
1939 Honorary Sc. D. University of Denver
1945 Trudeau Medal, National Tuberculosis Association
1947 Jane Addams Medal
1947 Sc. D. (Honorary) Colorado State College of Medicine
1947 Achievement Medal, University of Colorado
1947-1951 Interim chairman and Manager of Denver Dept. of Health and Welfare
1948 American Woman's Association Medal
1948 President, Western Branch, American Public Health Association
1950 Sc. D. (Honorary) Woman's Medical College of Pennsylvania
1951 Chairman, Denver Board of Health and Hospitals
1951 Lasker Award, American Public Health Association
1953 Distinguished Service Award, University of Colorado
1953 Died October 3, Denver Colorado
First woman...
1917 To be elected to full professorship at The Johns Hopkins School of Medicine
1924 To become President of the American Association of Anatomists
1925 To become full Member at The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
Scope and Contents note
Papers, Biography; photographs, selected reprints.
Consists primarily of photographs and newspaper items and articles about Florence Sabin.
Includes biography by Elinor Bluemel and National Academy of Sciences Biographical Memoir written by Philip McMaster and Michael Heidelberger.
Includes:.
Mary Kay Phelan, Probing the Unknown.
Acceptance of the Statue of Florence Rena Sabin by U.S. Congress.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 450 Sa13
Related Archival Materials note
The bulk of the Florence Rena Sabin Papers are to be found at The American Philosophical Society, Philadelphia, Inventory of boxes 1-6 "A-D" in box.
Conditions Governing Access note
This collection is open for research.
Biology -- Research; Cell and biomolecular sciences; Medical sciences; Medicine, Preventive; Biochemistry; Pathology; Bacteria; Bacteriology; Diseases; Medical research; Life sciences; Rockefeller University; Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research; Sabin, Florence Rena
- American Philosophical Society. Guide to Papers 1978. "A-D" only, 2½" letter (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Bibliographies (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1897-1952, 15 pp
  - 1897-1941
- Biographical. General, 1897-1941; 12 pp (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - F.R. Sabin/W.J. MacNeal re Dr. Baylis' work in the use of the floculation test for detecting spontaneous tuberculosis, 1927 October 19
  - H.C. Urey/F.R. Sabin re election of Josiah Willard Gibbs to Hall of Fame (Dr. Sabin elected to), 1935 July 3
  - The Pueblo Star-Journal, "Dr. Florence Sabin Speaks to Lions Thursday on Health", 1947?
    Scope and Contents note
    [Pencilled note on top of copy "Copies from material sent by Dr. Lawrence Kubie."].
    Carbon copies of typescript from news clips.
  - "Conference Center Cites, Singer, Scientist" re Florence Sabin and Kate Smith recipients of the 1947 arts and science citation of The National Conference of Christians and Jews in Chicago, 1947 May 17; carbon copies of typescript from news clips
- Biographical. L.S. Kubie article "Florence Rena Sabin" In: Perspectives in Biology and Medicine 4 (1961) 306-315., Reprint (Box 1, Folder 4)
- McMaster, Philip D. and Heidelberger, Michael, "Florence Rena Sabin, 1897-1953" NAS Biographical Memoirs 34 (1960) 271-319., 2 reprints (duplicate marked) (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Book Plate of Dr. Sabin's (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Given by Clara Lynch.
- Clippings. Photocopies of (Box 1)
  - Getts, John, "Florence Rena Sabin Was a Great Lady". Free Press, Colorado Springs, Colo, 1969 August 31 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "MD Remembers: Dr. Florence Sabin." MD, 1971 December (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Dr. Florence Sabin Was Pioneer of Public Health". Times-Call, Longmont, Colo, 1975 December 22 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - M.J. Zambo, "Skills Were'Sum of Rare Person". News-Sun, Springfield, Ohio, 1979 June 3 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Booth, Alice. "America's Twelve Greatest Women - Dr. Florence Rena Sabin." Good Housekeeping June 1931 (magazine article), 1931 June (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Photographs, 2½" letter
  - Portrait by Louis Schmidt, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Portrait, 1933-1934; various sizes (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Portraits, 1941 1946 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    1946 portrait signed by Dr. Sabin and taken by Windsor Studios, N.Y.C.
  - Portrait at Microscope (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Used in George W. Corner's, "History...".
  - Portraits. Drawing and Paintings (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Drawing of Dr. Sabin by R. Kastor?, Date?
      Scope and Contents
      [of painting by Geoffrey Coale. Information from: Elinor Bluemel, "Florence Sabin, Colorado Woman of the Century," 1959. University of Colorado Press]
    - Copies of painting of Dr. Sabin., 1931
      By Leon Gordon Information from same source as above.
    - For Dr. Sabin's 30th birthday by Gleb Ilyin, 1951; Portrait in color
  - Portraits, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Portraits. Lab Groups (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Lab groups, 1930 June 23; 2 photographs
    - Lab group, undated; 1 photograph
  - Mall, F.P. (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - F.P. Mall, 3 photographs
    - Dr. Mall's birthplace, 1 photograph
  - Photos. Miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Passport photos, 1928 June 6
    - Florence R. Sabin at right of photo, 1933 June
    - Composite of various photographs of Florence R. Sabin
      Includes 1 from New York Times, Nov 10, 1935 at 50th anniversary of founding of Bryn Mawr College. Dr. Sabin, President Emeritus of College receiving M. Carey Thomas prize w/ Dr. Marion Parks (president) and Simon Flexner.
      Includes other photos, some at Colorado State Board of Health.
- Presentation ceremony at Bryn Mawr College of M. Carey Thomas Award on November 2, 1935. Recorded by Station WEAF, 1 package. 4 phonodiscs (8 sides) (Package 1)
- Collected Reprints, 1 volume
- Elinor Bluemel, "Florence Sabin, Colorado Woman of the Century" University of Colorado Press, 1959
- Mary Kay Phelan, "Probing the Unknown, The Story of Dr. Florence Sabin" New York, Thomas Y. Crowell Co., 1969